

Abhishek Prasad

| +91 7003305184 | abhishekonit@gmail.com | LinkedInProfile

Data Science and Analytics professional with 10+ years of experience in verticals like CPG, Retail, Supply chain and Manufacturing Analytics, Pharma Analytics, Insurance Fraud Analytics, Capital markets and Manufacturing.

With continuous self-learning habits and client centric focus, I am always open to take out of comfort zone challenges and acquire new skill sets to stay relevant and update to date as per the market.

Professional Experience

Tredence Analytics Pvt. Ltd. Manager, Data Science

Aug, 2024 - Till Date

- Predictive modelling to identify the shipping errors resulting in credit losses. Causal decomposition to identify the reasons. Statistical Credit Fraud analysis of the retailers.
- Development of a Forecasting Model followed by Inventories policy based optimisation for a wholesale organisation supplying to the retail stores.
- Led the team to develop a tool to analyze drivers impacting the brand's ITR. The project includes multiple use cases like Clustering, Driver Analysis, Impact Analysis and Forecasting.
- Development of a Multi-Modal AI agent for diving deep into the data to perform driver analysis and derive insights for the end user.
- Development of a MAC based Al Agent POC to solve use cases like Anomaly detection, forecasting etc by refining the query and selecting the right sub-agent.

Fractal Analytics Pvt. Ltd.

Consultant - II

Supply Chain Finance (Aug, 2023 - Aug, 2024)

- Led an engagement to develop an Intelligent cash management product to determine the Credit worthiness and the Order Pattern of a customer.
- Forecasting the sales quantity across multiple countries on weekly data.
- POC on Inventory Optimization and Sustainability Analysis. Optimized the inventory data to minimize the waste.

Product Team - Concordia (Aug, 2021 - July, 2023)

As a lead member, contributed towards the Al-ML development of the product with primary focus on Research and Development of the new use cases.

Developed and operationalized the following ML models:

- Entity Extraction/Recognition Extracts entities from the unstructured data and transforms into a structural form that can consumed by other layers and data visualization tools. Implemented Machine Learning and NLP based models.
- Data Classification Classification of products based on their descriptions and other attributes through Machine Learning and NLP models.
- Data Mapping Mapping the products coming from different sources and have different textual representations. Developed a solution to map UPC and EAN code of a product. Rule based mechanism, Unsupervised and Supervised Machine Learning, and NLP models were tried and implemented.
- Volume and Metric Extraction Developed an ML based algorithm to extract volume and unit from product description column and standardize them. Algorithm has a minimum accuracy of 95%.
- Data Standardization Developed a NLP based entity standardization algorithm that uses multiple techniques and shows output according to defined similarity threshold.
- MDM creation Leveraged Unsupervised learning and mathematical distances to create Master data from multiple data coming from multiple retailers.
- Incremental Learning Enhance the learning of models if corrections are done by the user on the portal.
- Developed a prototype of data validation module from scratch that would raise flags for inconsistencies in data. Rule based KPI and Statistical metrics were used to build a prototype with Python and Streamlit.
- Created an end-to-end solution that would fetch data from Sharepoint, do preprocessing, feature engineering, KPI quantification, post-processing and share the results on Power BI dashboard. Created 100+ components in Python for data manipulation and developed the pipelines.

PRIMARY SKILL SET

Machine Learning, Statistical Analysis, Natural Language Processing, Gen Al Python, Spark, SQL Databricks, Azure ML, GCP (Vertex Al)

SECONDARY SKILL SET

Git, Power BI, Streamlit, Alteryx

INTERPERSONAL SKILL SET

Consulting, Team management, Stakeholders management, Research & Development

VERTICALS

CPG, Supply Chain, Manufacturing Capital Markets, Insurance

EDUCATION

Post Graduation Program in Business Analytics (Full-Time Program)

Praxis Business School, Kolkata, India 2018 - 2019

Bachelor of Technology Electronics and Communication Engineering

West Bengal University of Technology, India 2009 - 2013

LEARNING CURVE

 Exploring, learning and upgrading with the latest development in the field of Gen Al.



Abhishek Prasad

| +91 7003305184 | abhishekonit@gmail.com | LinkedIn Profile

Axtria India Pvt Ltd.

Mar, 2021 - Aug, 2021

Senior Associate

- Developed a model to classify whether the Physician would prescribe medicine manufactured by the client or not. The ML model resulted in an effective marketing.
- Developed a POC with multi-layer engine of Unsupervised learning and Rule-based method to authenticate Covid test reports.
- Re-designed existing Alteryx workflow for weekly and monthly reporting dashboards.

Bridgei2i Analytics Pvt. Ltd. (Acquired by Accenture) Analytics Consultant

Insurance Fraud Analytics (Sept, 2020 - March, 2021)

- Developed and operationalised a classification model to identify anomalous insurance claims filed due to bodily injury by automobile vehicle accident. Built multiple models and selected an XGB classifier as the final model.
- Developed an ML based Product Recommendation System to help the marketing team in cross-selling of the products. Enhanced Cross selling by 12-15%.
- Developed and operationalised an Operations Fraud project to identify and flag the fraud cases of payments by the performer to the participants.
- Migrated a project from SAS to Python as an Individual contributor. Data collection through SQL queries, model development and optimisation.

Supply Chain Analytics (Aug, 2019 - Aug, 2020)

- Developed an engine for Raw Materials Procurement Cost Anomaly Detection. Identified, defined and quantified the KPIs to calculate cost leakage in the procurement process. Created a business impact of 18-20%.
- Developed an ML based algorithm to identify similar products based on RM & PM. to utilise an alternate manufacturing lines by doing minimum changes during Covid lockdown. The solution was accepted as an all-time Reusable Asset.
- Build Plan designing and optimisation followed by Inventory Optimisation.
- Developed a ML based forecasting model to beat the benchmark score for a digital communications technology company. Material segmentation, feature engineering and selection, model development.
- Developed 2 different models for an FMCG company to do the demand forecasting.
 Material categorization and segmentation, feature engineering and selection, model development, model tuning and final selection.

Nevaeh Technology Quantitative Analyst

Oct, 2018 - July, 2019

- Building ML/DL models to predict the stock prices under different indices. Worked on Statistical analysis of the Stock prices. Time Series Forecasting for commodities price.
- Collaborating in the building of Trading Algorithms. Testing Trading Algorithm through Virtual Trade Simulation.
- Developed Python algorithms to:
 - Automate Back testing Simulation.
 - Calculate the Mark to Market (MTM) Profit and Stock's position.
 - Automate daily report for Net and Gross MTM
 - Stock exchange's Data (tar format) preparation with in-house tools.

Bhushan Steel Ltd (Acquired by Tata Steel) Electrical Engineer

Production Planning and Control (Mar, 2016 - Dec, 2017)

- Material demand forecasting. Report creation and sharing across.
- · Production demand plan scheduling.
- Inventory planning. Indentation management.
- Developed a POC on Sound Anomaly Detection System for Predictive maintenance.

▶ Hot Strip Mill (Shift-in-charge) (Sept, 2014 - Feb, 2016)

- Fault analysis and troubleshooting at hand through Ladder and CFC programming on Simatic manager for PLC (S7-300 and S7-400) at production finishing machines like cut to length, hot skin pass mill and slitter.
- Handling the conveyor system, fault analysis and resolutions for the coil conveyor system through HMI.

Education Mentor

UPGRAD Education Pvt. Ltd.

Post Graduate Students Mentor
Online Weekend Freelance
Mar 2022 - Aug 2022

Great Learning Education
Pvt. Ltd.

Post Graduate Students Mentor
Online Weekend Freelance
Sept 2021 - July 2022

COURSES

- AWS Fundamentals Coursera
- AWS Cloud Solutions Architect (Ongoing) - Coursera
- NLP Specialization by DeepLearning.Ai
- Modelling and Analytics in Supply Chain - IIT KGP
- Industry 4.0 and Industrial IoT -IIT KGP
- Google Cloud Big Data and ML Fundamentals
- Natural Language Processing -Edx

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

- House Price Prediction
- Pattern Recognition
- Sales Forecasting
- Language Translation
- Attempted to develop scripts for Algorithmic Trading.
 Developed Python script for all the technical indicators to analyze stocks.

LANGUAGE

- English
- Hindi
- Bengali